Bert L. Long, Jr. Papers AAA 7098
Museum of Fine Arts, Houston, Texas Art Project Microfilm
Bert L. Long, Jr. Papers
1975-1982
Museum of Fine Arts, Houston, Texas Art Project Microfilm
Long, Bert L.
AAA 7098
1,331 Images
Biographical / Historical
Bert L. Long Jr. (1940-2013) was born in Houston,TX. He has been judged as one of Texas's most important artists and gained world recognition during his lifetime. Self taught, he mastered a variety of mediums and won the National Endowment for the Arts grant (1987) and the Prix de Rome Fellowship (1990). During the 90's he worked extensively outside Texas, having studios in Rome, Italy and Spain. He described his paintings as a "quest to the inner self". Bert initiated the Project Row Houses movement along with six other African-American artists. His work is collected nationally and internationally at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, Dallas Art Museum, Museum Fine Arts Houston, Instituto de Bachillerato in Spain, among others.
Visit his website for more information: http://www.bertlong.com/html/index.htm
Sources: artnet, Bert Long, http://www.artnet.com/artists/bert-long/, acessed May 22nd, 2020.
Glasstire, Bert Long Texas Art Paradigm, 1940-2013, https://glasstire.com/2013/02/01/bert-long-1940-2013/, accessed May 22nd, 2020.
Bert, http://www.bertlong.com/html/index.htm, accessed May 22nd, 2020.
Scope and Contents
6 scrapbooks; correspondence; clippings; writings; subject files on the International Sculpture Conference, a project called 20/20, Artists in Action, and the Houston Contemporary Artists and Models Ball, 1979; pencil sketches for an ice sculpture; clippings of cooking columns written by Long; copies of "Houston ArtScene" magazine and other printed materials.
Other Finding Aids
AAA online guide at https://www.aaa.si.edu/collections/bert-l-long-jr-papers-7908.
Conditions Governing Access
Microfilm rolls 2890-2891 is available at the Museum of Fine Arts, Houston (Library), 1001 Bissonnet, Houston, Texas 77005, at the Detroit office of the AAA and through interlibrary loan.
Acquisition Information
Lent for microfilming 1983 by Bert L. Long, Jr. Originals returned to Bert L. Long, Jr. after microfilming.
Note: The Bert L. Long, Jr. Papers were microfilmed for the Texas Art Project at the Museum of Fine Arts, Houston as part of the Smithsonian Institution's Archives of American Art. Currently the papers can be accessed on microfilm at MFAH. The University of Houston Libraries and the Museum of Fine Arts, Houston are digitizing the Long papers as part of a collaborative TexTreasures 2020 grant project through the Texas State Library and Archives Commission (TSLAC) with funding from the U.S. Institute of Museum and Library Services (IMLS).When digitization is complete, the Long papers will be made available online through UH Libraries and MFAH websites.
Related Materials
The University of Houston Libraries Special Collections holds the Bert Long, Jr. papers.
Ice carving; African American Artists; Artists, Black; TexTreasures -- 2020
- Scrapbook, 1975-1982
  - 1975-1977 (Reel 2890, Image 4-43)
  - 1978 (Reel 2890, Image 44-105)
  - 1979 (Reel 2890, Image 106-167)
  - 1980 (Reel 2890, Image 168-288)
  - 1981 (Reel 2890, Image 289-352)
  - 1982 (Reel 2890, Image 353-398)
- Correspondence, 1977-1982; undated (Reel 2890, Image 399-616)
- Clippings, 1975-1982 (Reel 2890, Image 617-718)
- Writings (Reel 2890, Image 719-721)
- International Sculpture, Oakland, 1982 (Reel 2890, Image 722-746)
- La Concorde Ice Sculpture Sketches (Reel 2890, Image 747-759)
- Project 20/20, 1981 (Reel 2890, Image 760-781)
- Artists in Action (AIA), 1979 (Reel 2890, Image 782-891)
- Cooking Columns (Reel 2890, Image 892-919)
- Houston Contemporary Artists and Models Ball, 1979 (Reel 2890, Image 920-976)
- Bert Long and Floyd Newsum Exhibition, O'Kane Gallery, 1981 (Reel 2891, Image 5-14)
- Rejections, juried show entries (Reel 2891, Image 15-97)
- Art Scene, 1980-1982
  - Art Scene copies, 1980-1982 (Reel 2891, Image 98-319)
  - Art Scene correspondence, 1981-1982 (Reel 2891, Image 320-351)